{{short description|American businesswoman (1849–1898)}}
{{for|the Julia Tuttle Causeway|Interstate 195 (Florida)}}
{{Infobox person
| name         = Julia DeForest Tuttle|
| image        = File:Julia DeForest Tuttle.jpg|
| caption      = Portrait of Julia DeForest Tuttle
| birth_date   = {{birth date|1849|1|22|mf=y}}|
| birth_place  = [[Cleveland]], Ohio, U.S.
| death_date   = {{death date and age|1898|9|14|1849|1|22|mf=y}}|
| death_place  = [[Miami]], Florida, U.S.
| spouse      = Frederick Leonard Tuttle
| children     = 2 
<!--| net_worth  = $3.7m-->
}}
'''Julia DeForest Tuttle''' (née '''Sturtevant'''; January 22, 1849<ref>{{cite book| last = Wright | first = E. Lynne | title = More Than Petticoats: Remarkable Florida Women | publisher = TwoDot | year = 2001 | location = Guilford, Conn. | pages = 22 | isbn = 978-1-56044-993-5}}</ref> – September 14, 1898) was an American businesswoman who owned the property upon which [[Miami]], Florida, was built. For her boosterism, she's called the "Mother of Miami." She is the only woman to have founded what would become a major American city.<ref>{{Cite web|url=https://parade.com/256292/claudiagryvatzcopquin/whats-the-one-major-american-city-founded-by-a-woman/|title=What's the One Major American City Founded by a Woman?|first=Claudia Gryvatz|last=Copquin|date=January 23, 2014|website=Parade}}</ref>

==Early life==
Julia Sturtevant was the daughter of [[Ephraim Sturtevant]], a Florida planter and state senator.  She married Frederick Leonard Tuttle on January 22, 1867. They had two children: a daughter, Frances Emeline (b. 1868), and a son, Henry Ethelbert (b. 1870). Julia Tuttle first saw the [[Biscayne Bay]] region of [[South Florida metropolitan area|southern Florida]] in 1875 with her husband, visiting a 40-acre (16 ha) orange grove her father had purchased. She loved the experience, but returned to [[Cleveland, Ohio]], with her family.{{citation needed|date=November 2015}}

==Move to Southern Florida==
Tuttle came to [[Fort Dallas]], Florida, from Cleveland, Ohio, on a steamship after her father and mother had moved to South Florida. A little over ten years later, in 1886, her husband died; the foundry had already been sold. Upon his death, she found that her husband had not been good at managing money. This placed Julia in dire financial straits. To supplement her small income, she had to turn their four-story home into a boarding house and tearoom for young ladies.  In 1890, when her father died and left her his land in Florida, she sold her home in Cleveland, Ohio, and relocated to Biscayne Bay.{{citation needed|date=November 2015}}

Tuttle used the money from her parents' estate to purchase the James Egan grant of {{convert|640|acre|km2}}, where the city of Miami is now located, on the north side of the [[Miami River (Florida)|Miami River]], including the old Fort Dallas stone buildings, and the two-story rock house built by Richard Fitzpatrick's enslaved workers some 50 years earlier. This was converted into her home. In 1891, Tuttle brought her family to live there. She repaired and converted the home into one of the show places in the area with a sweeping view of the river and Biscayne Bay.<ref>Andrew K. Frank. Before the Pioneers: Indians, Settlers, Slaves, and the Founding of Miami (University Press of Florida, 2017)</ref> She stated in a letter to her friend “It may seem strange to you, but it is the dream of my life to see this wilderness turned into a prosperous country. Where this tangled mass of vine, brush, trees and rocks now are to see homes with modern improvements surrounded by beautiful grassy lawns, flowers, shrubs and shade trees.”<ref>{{Cite news |last=Sheppard |first=Elena |date=2021-12-03 |title=Overlooked No More: Julia Tuttle, the 'Mother of Miami' |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2021/12/03/obituaries/julia-tuttle-overlooked.html |access-date=2024-07-04 |work=The New York Times |language=en-US |issn=0362-4331}}</ref>

Tuttle saw the opportunity to found a new city on the Miami River, but knew that a [[railroad]] was necessary to attract development. Tuttle tried to induce [[Henry Flagler]] to extend his [[Florida East Coast Railway]]to Fort Dallas, and offered to divide her large real estate holdings as an enticement. After numerous fruitless letters she made the trip to St. Augustine and made a personal appeal, again unsuccessful. Good fortune for her expansionist ambitions too the form of the [[Great Freeze]] of 1894-1895, which devastated the old orange belt of central and northern Florida, wiping out valuable groves and fortunes alike.

Either Flagler recalled Tuttle's touting of the South Florida weather and sent some men to investigate, or Tuttle alerted Flagler that the freeze had spared the Miami River area, sending as evidence a bouquet of flowers and foliage (possibly oranges) as proof; the order to extend his railroad came. Under an agreement between the two, Tuttle supplied Flagler with the land for a hotel and a railroad station for free, and they split the remainder of her 640 acres (2.6&nbsp;km<sup>2</sup>) north of the Miami River in alternating sections. 

On February 15, 1896, Joseph B. Reilly, John Sewell, and E.G. Sewell, the vanguard of the Flagler forces, arrived, and the work of building the Royal Palm Hotel was commenced.{{citation needed|date=November 2015}} On April 22, 1896, train service of the Florida East Coast Railway came to the area. On July 28, male residents voted to incorporate a new city, Miami. Steady growth followed.{{citation needed|date=November 2015}}

==Death==
In 1898, Tuttle fell ill with apparent [[meningitis]]. Plans were made to move her to [[Asheville, North Carolina]], by rail for treatment, but her condition deteriorated before she could be transported. She died on September 14, 1898, at age 49. Her funeral took place at her Fort Dallas home, and she was buried in a place of honor at the [[City of Miami Cemetery]]. Her tombstone notes her year of birth as 1848, while other sources list 1849.

==Legacy==
Tuttle died leaving a large amount of debt, partly the result of her land grant incentives to Flagler. Her children sold her remaining land to pay it off. Her name was mostly forgotten until it was placed on a causeway for [[Interstate 195 (Florida)|Interstate 195]] over Biscayne Bay.{{when|date=September 2025}} In contrast, the name of [[William Brickell]], a large landowner on the south side of the Miami River who contributed to Tuttle's efforts to incorporate the city, appeared widely on the south side of what became Miami.<ref>{{Cite web |last=Kleinman |first=Jeff |date=March 7, 2023 |title=What did Miami's Brickell Avenue used to look like? These old photos show the changes |url=https://www.miamiherald.com/news/local/community/miami-dade/downtown-miami/article272663833.html |website=Miami Herald}}</ref>

Just as Tuttle is called the [[List of people known as the father or mother of something|Mother of Miami]], Flagler became known as the [[List of people known as the father or mother of something|Father of Miami]]. Both Tuttle and Brickell had previously lived in [[Cleveland]], where they first met.{{citation needed|date=November 2015}}

In addition to the Julia Tuttle Causeway, the memory of Tuttle has been honored with a sculpture in [[Bayfront Park]], by Daub and Firmin.<ref>{{cite web | title=Julia Tuttle statue arrives | publisher=The Miami Herald | url=http://www.miamiherald.com/2010/07/27/1747814/julia-tuttle-statue-arrives.html | date=27 July 2010 | access-date=28 July 2010 | author=Kelly House}}</ref> Additionally, the large downtown Miami food hall, Julia & Henry's, is named for her and Flagler.

Julia Tuttle inspired several projects of the [[Miami Girls Foundation]] and the Miami Girls Manifesto written by [[Rebecca Fishman-Lipsey]].<ref>{{Cite AV media |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J5J1PmOl8To |title=Miami Girls Foundation Manifesto |date=2017-05-30 |last=Miami Girls Foundation |access-date=2025-08-19 |via=YouTube}}</ref>
<gallery>
File:JuliaTutteMiami.jpg|Julia Tuttle statue in Bayfront Park - Miami
File:Julia tuttle tomb 02.jpg|Julia Tuttle memorial marker in the Miami City Cemetery
</gallery>

== References ==

{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
{{Portal|Biography}}
*Akin, Edward N.. The Cleveland Connection: Revelations from the John D. Rockefeller - Julia Tuttle Correspondences. In ''Tequesta: the Journal of the Historical Association of Southern Florida'', no. XLII (1982). [http://digitalcollections.fiu.edu/tequesta/files/1982/82_1_03.pdf] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120222195318/http://digitalcollections.fiu.edu/tequesta/files/1982/82_1_03.pdf |date=2012-02-22 }}
*Frank, Andrew K. Before the Pioneers: Indians, Settlers, Slaves, and the Founding of Miami (University Press of Florida, 2017)
*Peters, Thelma. ''Biscayne Country, 1870-1926''. Miami, Fla.: Banyan Books, c1981.
*Tuttle Family Papers. Finding aid. [http://www.historymiamiarchives.org/tuttle-family-papers-1889-1954 Tuttle Family Papers - 1889-1954 -]
*Wiggins, Larry. The Birth of the City of Miami. In ''Tequesta: the Journal of the Historical Association of Southern Florida'', no. LV (1995). [http://digitalcollections.fiu.edu/tequesta/files/1995/95_1_01.pdf] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120222195336/http://digitalcollections.fiu.edu/tequesta/files/1995/95_1_01.pdf |date=2012-02-22 }}

==Further reading== 
* {{Cite news|last=Sheppard|first=Elena|date=2021-12-03|title=Overlooked No More: Julia Tuttle, the 'Mother of Miami'|language=en-US|work=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2021/12/03/obituaries/julia-tuttle-overlooked.html|access-date=2021-12-29|issn=0362-4331}}

{{Florida Women's Hall of Fame}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tuttle, Julia}}
[[Category:1849 births]]
[[Category:1898 deaths]]
[[Category:American city founders]]
[[Category:American businesspeople in the real estate industry]]
[[Category:Businesspeople in agriculture]]
[[Category:History of Miami]]
[[Category:19th-century American businesspeople]]
[[Category:Businesspeople from Miami]]
[[Category:19th-century American businesswomen]]
[[Category:Florida Women's Hall of Fame Inductees]]
